<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majesties message to both houses of Parliament at Westminster, sent from Oxford 23. Martii, 1645.</title>
            <title>Miscellaneous Documents. 1646-03-23</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B19045</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99886206</idno>
  <idno type="VID">188398</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240890821</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing C2460</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 1851.b.3[45]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R225687</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99886206</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99886206e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B19045)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 188398)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C10:2[48])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majesties message to both houses of Parliament at Westminster, sent from Oxford 23. Martii, 1645.</title>
                  <title>Miscellaneous Documents. 1646-03-23</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1625-1649 : Charles I)</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Leonard Lichfield, printer to the Vniversity,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645 [i.e. 1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dates are given according to Lady Day dating.</note>
                  <note>Steele notation: an- more afflicted.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="King_to_Parliament">
            <pb facs="tcp:188398:1"/>
            <head>His MAJESTIES Message to both Houses of Parliament at <hi>Westminster,</hi> sent from <hi>Oxford</hi> 23. <hi>Martii,</hi> 1645.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>To be read in all Churches and Chappells, whereby the People may rest satisfied how great a desire His</hi> MAjESTY <hi>hath to ease them of the burthen of the Warre.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>CHARLES R.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Otwithstanding the unexpected silence, in stead of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to His Majesties many and Gratious Messages to both Houses, whereby it might appeare that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to obtain their ends by Force, rather then Treaty, which might justly discourage His Majesty from any more overtures of that kind; yet His Majesty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives, that He should be too much wanting in His duty to God, and in what He owes to the safety of His People, if He should not endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to prevent the great inconveniences, which might otherwise hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a safe and well grounded Peace.</p>
            <p>His Majesty therefore now proposeth, That (so He may have the Faith of His two Houses of Parliament, for the preservation of His Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Person, and Estate, and that liberty be given to all those that doe, and have adhered to His Majesty, to goe to their own Houses, and there to live peaceably, enjoying their Estates, (all Sequestrations being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off) without being compelled to take any Oath, not enjoyn'd by the undoubted Lawes of the Kingdom, or being put to any other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestation whatsoever) He will then immediatly disband all His Forces, and dismantle all His Garrisons, and (being accompanied with His Royall, not Martiall Attendants) returne to His two Houses of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and there reside with them.</p>
            <p>And for the better security of all His Majesties Subjects, He propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, That He with the said two Houses, immediatly upon His com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to <hi>Westminster,</hi> doe passe an Act of Oblivion and free Pardon: and where His Majesty will farther doe whatsoever they shall advise Him unto, for the Peace and good of this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>As for the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> His Majesty hath made no mention of it herein, in regard of the great losse of time, which must needs be spent in expecting an answer from thence: But declares, that immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon His comming to <hi>Westminster,</hi> He will apply Himselfe to give them all satisfaction touching that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>If His Majesty could possibly doubt the successe of this offer, He might use many Arguments to perswade them to it; But shall only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist on that great One, Of giving an instant Peace to these afflicted Kingdomes.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at the Court at Oxford, <date>the 23. of <hi>March.</hi> 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>For the Speaker of the House of Peeres <hi>pro tempore,</hi> to be commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to the two Houses of Parliament at <hi>Westminster,</hi> and the Commissioners of the Parliament of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at <hi>Oxford,</hi> by <hi>Leonard Lichfield,</hi> Printer to the Vniversity. 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>